this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at SC - radio dotnet.
SC radio is brought to you by the I Triple E Computer Society I.
Triple E software magazine online at computer org slash software. developers are you ready.
it's time.
to upgrade your data platform to inner systems iris.
choose your language choose your tools choose your environment collaborate build faster and deploy more efficiently.
when you can make faster decisions there's no telling what you'll create.
ready set code start coding.
for free visit inner systems comm slash try to try iris.
hello everyone this is Felina for software engineering radio today with me on the show with Sam Gav's use him.
he graduated from Princeton University with a degree in computer science in 2015 and he is the founder of byte by byte.
that helps software engineers interview for jobs at top tech companies.
use the also the author of dynamic programming interviews the e-book that helps anyone succeed at dynamic programming interviews.
welcome to the show Kevin. thank you.
so much for having me so the topic of today's show is technical interviews.
and let's start with the basics can you take us to the typical process that a company would go to if they're hiring someone.
yeah absolutely so you know we tend to work with primarily people who are looking for jobs at companies like a Google or a Facebook or something like that.
sort of the high level tech companies and there's generally a process where you know you're gonna start by either you apply or.
a lot of times if you already have experience as a software engineer a recruiter might actually reach out to you.
so that's a really good reason why you should have a good LinkedIn profile because you can kind of put yourself out there.
but then after that you're probably gonna get on a call with a recruiter and they're just gonna try and learn a little bit more about what your background is.
and how that relates to the role and make sure that just fundamentally you're a good.
fit and they're not necessarily gonna probably test you on anything technical.
but then after that you're gonna have a technical screen of some sort.
so we've been seeing a lot more companies doing online tech screens.
so you know you're gonna go on and you're gonna it'll essentially be like using leet code except they'll use whatever platform they're using.
then after that if you pass that you'll have a phone screen where you're gonna solve some technical questions.
and then finally if you pass through all that you're.
gonna end up in an on-site interview.
so you're gonna go and you're gonna have maybe four or five interviews over the course of a day.
and depending on the level those are gonna be it's gonna depend how many of those are like technical interviews versus behavioral versus systems.
it's a system design those are sort of the three things that you're going to see.
and obviously this process varies a lot from company to company so I don't want to say that all companies are like this but.
those are sort at least the components that you can expect to see as you're going through the interview process.
yes so typically there would be a number of steps it's definitely not just the one job interview but or a bunch of them.
and some parts can be very technical and other parts can be more about culture fit.
and typically even though there are differences between companies those both ingredients exist in the whole process right.
yeah exactly so you know there are those little variances but what.
I really try and encourage people to think about is the fact that the fundamentals don't change from company to company.
and even from type of interview to type of interview.
so for example if you're doing an online assessment versus a phone screen versus an on-site interview if they're all technical interviews it's the same thought process that applies.
and so you want to learn if you can learn how to be strategic about approaching those types of problems then that really applies to everything that you're doing and.
it's not like you're just saying okay let me go I have an Amazon technical screen coming up so let me go look at specifically how to prepare for that.
you want to think more generally how can I prepare for these technical problems as a whole.
and then apply that to the specific company that you're going to be interviewing.
yeah yeah so let's zoom into this technical interview part because that's the thing we're most interested in this episode.
even with in technical interviews there quite a lot.
of differences of course the canonical thing that people think of is like a whiteboard interview where you ask you're being asked to do an algorithm without a computer.
but nowadays I think it's also common to do coding challenges on the computer.
maybe even as you mentioned also online before or as part of the interview process.
what are different types of technical interviews that exhibit.
yeah there are quite a few different ways that you can be asked the question.
so again I would go back to the.
fact that fundamentally you're being asked to do the same thing regardless it's more the medium that's changing.
so like a lot of times the first step is going to be some online screen so there's no other person involved.
you're literally just going on the computer and they give you a prompt and you have to solve the problem.
and maybe you know you have 60 or 90 minutes and you have one or two problems and then there'll be automated tests.
so think like a hacker ranked problem.
or a leak code problem and so that's sort of usually that first step.
then you might be asked to do a phone screen where in that case you are also going to be coding on a computer.
but you're going to be using a shared editor.
so a lot of people like to use collab at it or if you're doing a Google interview you're gonna be happy.
you're gonna have to use Google Docs which kind of sucks or they're a bunch of other tools out there and.
some of them let you compile the code some of them let you do syntax highlighting different stuff and some of them don't.
and so with that what you really want to be prepared for is you want to be prepared for unless you know what platform they're using ahead of time.
you want to be prepared for the fact that you're not going to have all the tools that you're used to.
and then of course you're going into when you're going into the company there are a bunch.
of different things you can see so you could see that whiteboarding interview which is obviously still the most common.
I've also seen more things like debugging interviews or Google I believe now gives you the option to code on a computer.
it's sort of the same sort of interview but they'll give you a computer with an IDE.
and the thing to be careful with that is that that sounds like Oh obviously that's the best choice.
but realize that you don't get to choose what tech setup they.
have how that computer is configured.
so realize that even though that sounds like it might be a great thing you're kind of gonna get shoehorned into whatever they have available for you. so it's just something to be careful about with that as well.
because you don't want to assume that you're gonna be able to use your particular IDE with your you know all of your keyboard shortcuts and everything.
and they get in there and it's a totally different thing.
so those are a couple of the.
different ways that you might be approaching these problems.
but you know they're fundamentally the same problems and you're just put into a different setting to have to answer them.
and then what do companies look at so what are they interested in.
are they interested in people that just get it right or are they looking at what is your process.
and even if you don't manage to get the answer right then they look at what if the stuff you do what do you Google for.
what what.
are you looking for is that something that people do or is it really if you don't get the answer right then you're out.
so I like to think about it like those math tests that you have in grade school where they give you partial for showing your work.
because it really is something where the if we just think like if we take a step back here and think about what is the goal of the interview.
the goal of the interview is to learn whether this is.
a person that I would like to work with whether this is a person that I think would be a good fit for our company.
and specifically in this case a good fit from a technical standpoint.
and so what that means is that you know you do have to really show your work and show how you are actually getting to that answer.
so certainly just showing the perfect answer is not usually going to be enough or you're definitely shooting yourself in the foot.
because there is no.
there's no room for error there now beyond that there is it's really arranged.
so it depends a lot on what your specific interviewer is looking for.
but I've seen you know I was just speaking with a student the other day who said hey I did my Google phone screen the other day.
and I really felt like I screwed it up and then they just called me and asked me to come do an on-site.
and so you really it can be really hard to actually evaluate self.
evaluate how you're doing.
and it's really the case that there is such a broad range of the expectations of the interviewers that it's impossible to say generically.
like you know you have to have an answer that it's this degree of optimized or you have to have an answer that is this degree of correct right.
because it's such a spectrum. but in a broad broad scope the way that I think about it as an interviewer is I sort of have a cut-off point. like I have I've.
asked the same question again and again and so I have an idea of here's roughly where I expect a good candidate to end up.
and if you get beyond that if you do more then obviously you're a very good candidate.
and if you do a lot less than that you would have to make up for it in other ways.
you would have to be a really compelling candidate who I really connected with and really wanted to work with.
or really had great experience other than that.
for me to want to move you along to that next round.
but there's that rough cut off and that cut off is not necessarily finding the most optimal solution.
that cutoff could be I want you to get to at least a certain point in the problem.
or I want you to you know discover this property of the question that I'm asking you sort of thing.
so it really depends a lot on the problem and the interviewer but generally speaking you want to be careful of the.
mistake that I see people make is that they think that.
oh I didn't find the perfect solution and I'm kind of struggling with this problem.
and therefore my interviewer is automatically gonna fail me or they gave me a hint and so they're automatically gonna fail me.
and then they start to get in their head and they start to say oh well I already screwed this up.
so they end up flubbing the interview even though if they had just stuck with it they would have been fine.
because that's actually what the interviewer was expecting.
so hopefully that sort of gives a little bit more context around that anyway.
okay so where were we we were and you know what away if a candidate fails then when do they fail is it really a hit or miss.
but you said no oh so I look at the process and there are these things that and I might look at.
and if people get to a certain extent and they still get some grades for showing their work.
yeah exactly because it's you know one of those things that a lot of times I think that. people think.
people go into the interview with this expectation that I am going to I have to do X or else I'm gonna automatically fail.
and that's very much not the case it's very much there's a lot more nuance in it than that.
and so even if you don't feel like you're doing well you could actually pass on to the next round of the interview. you just need to.
keep sort of mentally with it keep mentally on your game even if you're not feeling great about it.
yeah so would you also be looking at soft skills of a candidate.
I would not necessarily so skills interview.
but I think in a coding exercise you can also see persistence maybe how patients are people with challenging questions.
how long did they keep pursuing a certain fad until they backtrack and see it's not the right bad.
so are you mainly focusing on the technical skills or do you.
also look at those soft skills that are very related to technical skills.
this is an interesting one because I think it's something that what I've found from experience is that generally the thing that screws people up is the technical side.
so I've really focused you know when I work with people I tend to focus more on that.
and what I see at least obviously we can talk about behavioral interviews as well which that's a totally different beast unto itself.
but if we're talking about the technical.
interview specifically the way that I generally look at it is that the technical skills are the make-or-break part.
and the social and sort of behavioral stuff is more of the icing on the cake.
so that's the thing that can push you one way or the other.
if you're on the fence about if the interviewer is on the fence about a candidate.
like if I really like you and this is what I was saying before about how there is some gray area in exactly what I would. and wouldn't accept.
because if you're sort of just at that point where I think that you know you're basically at that.
cutoff point and I really liked you.
I'm much more likely to push you ahead and say okay well let's say let's give him the benefit of the doubt give her the benefit of the doubt.
and say let's give them another interview and see what other people think.
because obviously you're gonna have to pass multiple interviews but lots of times we have one that doesn't go. as well as the others.
and so if I really like you I'm much more likely to say okay I'm essentially going to defer to everyone else.
because I thought their technical skills were good enough not the best that I've seen but they're good enough.
that if they did well elsewhere I'm happy working with them.
in the same way if I really didn't like someone.
then that would make it you know I I would tend to value the technical skills over whether I like someone or not.
but it's still something where if I was on the fence about it that might have an impact.
and I think it the one other piece that this affects which we don't really think about.
is how much an interviewer helps the candidate as they're going through the interview.
and how much they do that sort of subconsciously without actually saying I'm going to like deduct points from them.
because obviously if I give someone a hint the way that I usually think about it personally anyway is that each.
hint that I give them depending on the magnitude of the hint is some number of essentially imaginary points deducted from their total score.
I'm not keeping an actual score but just you know it's one sort of demerit.
yeah sure you have a sense of how much you've helped someone or whether they came up with the entire solution by themselves.
exactly and so if I had to help them a lot that's obviously counts off a lot more. but I do think that.
if I really like the.
person I'm more likely to subconsciously help them I'm more likely to provide encouragement.
I'm more likely to share and if they're very communicative I'm much more likely to discuss ideas with them.
and not really think of that as me giving them a hint because that was not my intention.
and so that's a much more subtle thing and it's not something where you know I'm doing it consciously.
but there's just so much value in how the dynamic changes when you like the person. then again I don't.
think it's the most important thing.
I think people should focus on the technical skills first and foremost because that can because if your technical skills are great the social part doesn't matter.
but in that middle ground it can really help you a lot.
now on the topic of collaborating with candidates have you seen people doing fair programming and interviews.
is this something you have experience with yourself or you've heard from people.
yeah I remember actually I did a pair of programming interview a wild pack with.
square I think it was did a pair of programming interview.
I think there that is one that I forgot to mention.
I think there's more of these sort of collaborative things which I think is a really great way to approach it.
the downside of that is obviously that it is much harder for people to judge in an objective way.
and so I think with things like that it really does come probably down a lot more to how you connect with the person. how like the social.
skills become more important in that sort of setting because it's not a matter of just they either got the answer or they didn't.
since it's this collaboration and so I'm not I've not conducted those.
so I'm not I not exactly sure how people usually think about that when they are evaluating them.
but just from a from my perspective it would seem to be something that would be a lot more had that on whether I like the person.
and whether I feel good working with them rather.
than whether they're technically the most proficient person.
yeah that would emphasize communication skills a little bit more.
and it's actually nicely segues into my next question.
because I was gonna ask do you typically use different types of interviews for different roles.
in some roles let's say a scrum master or product owner communication skills might be a bigger part of your job.
even though it's still a technical role then an otter role.
so would you say a tester or a DevOps person do they have different technical.
interviews or is everything the same apart from the type of technical questions that you ask them.
yeah great question because I do think it varies a lot.
and you know the more I will say as well that what we focus on is mostly with with the companies that we're focusing on.
they tend to be more of a generalist focus.
so it's not so much that you're hiring people for specific technical roles or even for things like a scrum master or these different types of roles. it.
tends to be more like software engineer tech lead manager and then maybe like DevOps and things like that.
so it's a fair it's a kind of more limited set of options.
but with that I do think that it's important to realize that.
there are different types of interviews.
and so it really what I found is that it more tends to be not that.
the interview the individual type like interview questions change.
but the ratio of different types of questions.
so it's like if I'm looking at.
like software engineering role purely software engineering then I'm probably going to.
if I'm a relatively junior person I might expect three technical interviews or four technical interviews and one system design interview or maybe one behavioral interview. and that's about it.
if you're getting further along if you're a more senior developer you might expect multiple system design interviews.
you might expect at least one maybe two behavioral interviews and fewer of the technical interviews.
and so it really I think more tends to shift the like ratio of.
different types of interviews then the questions themselves within each category shift if that makes sense.
and so and then also if you're looking at like more management type roles obviously you can expect more about behavioural types of questions around the management and leadership.
which the way that I would think about it broadly is there are two things that you can do.
one I highly recommend people go on glassdoor.com because you can see a lot of references and people will share their interview experiences.
they'll share what.
sorts of questions they were asked.
and so it can give you a lot of context and actually this is going to be three things too.
you can ask your recruiter what you should expect to be asked in the interview because the recruiter really is yeah.
because the recruiter is really a person who is they benefit from you getting the job they really want to support you and they're really there.
I a lot of times people get bent out of shape about recruiters but realize it's not.
because they hate you or anything it's because they have so many candidates that they're working with.
but they still have your best interest in a lot of cases and so it's good to reach out to them.
and see if you can figure out more about what to expect from the recruiter so that's number two and number three.
look at the role and put yourself in your interviewers shoes and think about for a second what would I want to see if I were the interviewer.
and how.
can I sort of extrapolate and imagine what I would ask the person if I was in that position.
so how aligned should interviews be to the actual job.
so we all know these difficult answers like reverse a link list or search through a binary tree but who does that really in a job.
so what is your take on that is there like a catalogue of questions that are good algorithmic questions to ask.
or shoot companies more aligned their questions with if you're gonna be a web.
front-end developer and and the exercise should also be something like make a form with a button and it should be responsive.
and more like your actual job what's your take on that.
it's kind of a loaded question but I'll talk a little bit about it. I think that.
this is one of the I mean this is just the debate right.
this is sort of the ongoing debate that I don't think is ever gonna end.
because I don't think it's ever gonna completely shift over to you.
know you're doing interviews that are exactly like what you're doing in your job is that's just not realistic.
and you know if you look at other industries too I think people tend to get more bent out of shape about this in software engineering than other industries.
but if you look at in interviews like you know think about if you were very simple example interviewing for a job as a hamburger flipper at McDonald's.
your job interview is not going to involve you going and flipping hamburgers. your.
job interview is gonna involve you like talking about yourself right.
so at a very basic level job interviews are never gonna be the same as the actual job.
that being said I do think there's value in trying to test people as well as you can in those relative skills.
and so you know I think that. there are pros and cons to all the different approaches.
and that's why a lot of people will say oh we'll just have people do a project right have them do a.
quick like web development project and then you can see whether or not they know how to do the job.
and that's great in theory but what that involves is that involves a lot of time outside of you know the actual interviews.
for the person doing the work you have no idea what kind of resources they use you have no idea whether they copied the code from someone else.
or you know whether they can actually do the job because you're not actually there to monitor their thought.
process on the flip side there's a downside to doing the technical interviews.
because obviously it is a very different skill set and it's a kind of awkward thing that people have to learn in and of themselves.
like learn completely separately from their job.
the way that I tend to think about this is I need to look up what this book was because I could never remember what the book is actually called.
but there was a book that I read and they talked about this idea of.
gravity problems and a gravity problem is a problem it's like gravity where you can complain about it all you want.
but that's not gonna make a bit of difference right.
I can complain about oh I hate gravity so much but that's not going to mean that the more I complain doesn't make it more likely.
I'm gonna be able to like jump off the roof of my building and fly right.
it just is not something that's going to change.
and so you have to work within the.
parameters that you're given and I think as an interviewer or as an interviewee you know we are in we are working within these parameters.
and so it's really a matter of learning how can I get the best at what I'm going to have to do at actually demonstrating these skills in my interview.
and not stress out about whether this is a quote-unquote fair process or not.
on the side of the interviewers we should always be looking for ways that better test people. and I do think.
that things like pair programming or projects or you know even just giving people an IDE to work with can be really valuable tools.
but you got to figure out a way to do that so that it's fair and that it's not like actually making more complexity and more difficulty for the candidates.
so honestly long answer short there's not really a great solution.
but you know I think that.
people tend to be overly negative about coding interviews and technical interviews.
and it's really something where if you. think about it in reality it's not that.
different from interviews in any other profession.
and it is something that is a learning and if you learn it that sets you up really well for your career down the road.
so it's something that I think is worth taking the time to learn and figure out how you can do it effective.
yeah it's definitely true of course from the side if someone is being interviewed.
but some people in our audience might also be the people that do the.
interviews and I would say from the side of the interviewer it's not really a gravity problem.
because you have full control over the things you ask within your company.
so yeah I totally see your saying that if you're an interviewee yeah you can complain but you're still gonna reverse the linked list.
but on the side of the interviewers there of course is where it gets interesting.
because it's not just a matter of fairness even though fairness is very important. it's also a matter of how well.
does this interview help me predict whether this person actually fits at the company.
whether they would be happy whether they would be productive.
so I can see apart from fairness then it also might make sense if your questions reflects what a candidate is gonna do.
just because you get a better sense of them.
or would you say that these technical interviews these like say algorithmic questions you think they're definitely always a good predictor for technical jobs.
for what I have seen and I think that's a.
is an interesting question from what I've seen I think that.
the algorithmic type questions tend to be an overly restrictive measure.
and so you know what I would say is that for the most part it's obviously not a hundred percent true.
but generally speaking if someone is a good is good at the algorithmic interviews. I think that is a pretty good indicator that.
they're going to be good at the actual job as well.
because it shows that they sort of from a thought process perspective and.
from a mindset perspective have the sort of technical know-how.
the downside of that though is that it does eliminate lots of people who might be great candidates but are not good at algorithmic questions.
so I think there are a lot of people where they're not necessarily good at algorithmic questions but they are good at software engineering.
they are good at like building products and stuff.
and so when you look at it you know from a company's perspective it's a very high cost for me to hire.
the wrong person and so I'd be I'd prefer to have something where I accidentally weed out good candidates rather than I accidentally let in bad candidates.
and so in that respect I think that there is value in that. from the company perspective.
and then on the flip side it means that as a software engineer you have to get good at answering those types of questions.
I think that's part of the reason why it's a relatively good indicator that someone is going to be a good developer.
is that you have to be strong from a technical standpoint to be able to get good at interviewing.
but the reason why there are a lot of people who aren't good at interviewing is that it's a separate skill.
so it's like a skill that builds on top of being a good engineer already if that makes sense. yeah and it does make some sense.
but I would also say that there's also some bias of course in each process.
because for example having a graduate degree or master's.
degree or a bachelor's degree in computer science will be one of the things that such interviews key built on top off.
because if you're if you go to university and you do computer science program which I did in university.
then you will definitely learn some of the things that they might ask in those interviews.
so do you think actually it is a benefit to have a formal computer science degree.
and do you agree with me that those interviews might be geared a bit towards people that. have a university degree.
or do you think if you're just a good technical think are you ask for programming skills you can still also learn the algorithmic scent.
it is unrelated to each other yeah a hundred.
I 100% agree with you that the interviews are sort of biased towards people with a degree.
and I you know I think that the problem that I see is that.
there's it's not like there's a great alternative solution.
and so I'm not I'm by no means want to say that.
this is a great solution but I don't think that there are I think that the other approaches that.
people have come up with also have a lot of problems.
and so you know I do think in that respect that getting a degree can be really helpful.
I have you know I was actually just speaking with a friend the other day who's considering doing a boot camp.
and I think there's a lot of you know you can definitely make that work as well but it is a.
bit of a harder road because you're not getting that same foundation that you are necessarily getting when you're doing a computer science degree.
and you know it's kind of the these types of interviews anyway are definitely biased towards people who have that foundation.
now I would say as well that there are a lot of jobs that don't ask these types of questions so it's not necessarily a requirement.
and I think there are a couple great github repos that I could look up but I don't know.
off the top of my head where people talk about like for example jobs that don't ask coding type questions in the interviews.
and there are a lot of great companies that don't ask these types of questions.
so if that's something where you know it's really hard for you or you're really struggling that is an option as well.
as to just say I'm not going to do this I'm going to look at other companies.
calling all developers there's no telling what you can create when you upgrade.
your data platform to inner systems iris are you ready to build the applications you want.
however you want them are you ready to develop applications faster than ever.
collaborate build faster and deploy more efficiently.
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are waiting for you today.
inner system's IRS Data Platform ready set code.
start coding for free visit inner systems comm / try to try iris.
so you mentioned in your answer you said well there are also other approaches apart from technical interviews that also have problems.
and I think.
you mentioned one example which is the bootcamp what would be other approaches.
so consider consider a company would wanna maybe diversify developers they hire and this change something and not through the technical interviews.
what are things people could use that are other approaches and maybe also what would be their problems.
also the general things that I see in terms of evaluating developers are you know.
you have the sort of standard technical interviews and then you have different like variations on that.
so you have the pair.
programming which we already talked about is much more biased towards the social ability than it is towards the technical side.
we have other sorts of interviews like you could do like a debugging interview.
or you could do a you know perfect example is with what I mentioned earlier on is Google giving people a computer that they can use.
but it's not their computer and so it's this whole different set up it's this whole you know it can make it a lot it can actually put you.
into a very uncomfortable environment that you're not familiar with.
so that's you know its own set of downsides.
then you also have stuff like having people do projects which that's the other thing that I see coming up a lot is having people do some sort of project.
but you run into the issue there with a couple different things.
one is that you you know have people having to do a lot of work outside of the interview.
like I remember when I was in college I had.
a company ask me to do this and I probably spent 20 hours working on this project like 20 hours that I basically didn't have.
so that was really but I really wanted the job.
and so I was in a position where I was willing to do it even though maybe I shouldn't have invested that much effort.
and you also have the difficulty of grading those projects because you don't know what kind of work went in.
you don't actually know if I give someone a week to.
do project and I'm like I want someone who can do this whole thing in four hours.
I don't know how long they spent when they were doing it on their own.
and I don't know what resources they were using.
I don't know what you know potentially people could copy paste code from Stack Overflow and have no idea how it actually works.
right - I'm not saying that there's necessarily that this is the wrong way to do it but it definitely has its own set of problems.
and one option that I think does have potential is bringing people on for is paying people to do small projects.
but the downside of that of course is that you know it's hard for people to integrate into your platform in a short period of time.
and so you're essentially paying them to do toy projects which is expensive on the company's behalf.
so there are a lot of different ways that you could approach it but I think they all have different sorts of flaws.
and they all.
emphasize different characteristics.
you know let's go back to the technical interviews in itself and then the biases in these.
a while ago you said as an answer like if I give someone help then I mentally deduct a point from their score.
so of course people have biases and it's very hard to do that sort of thing without unintentionally also taking into account.
the person that is sitting opposite you.
so things that you might accidentally take into account you know women of women you might earlier think.
they don't really know they don't understand right over men you might think yeah they know but it just phrased it a little bit weird or something.
and the same might be true for racial biases or for people with disabilities.
so is there anything that you do to counter those biases within technical interviews.
so I personally have not had too much experience with that specific thing.
I I think that this is one of those things that.
is kind of a again a perennial issue with interviewing. no.
matter what kind of interviews you're doing and no matter what sort of situation.
one one example of people trying to address this that I've seen is interviewing IO does anonymous interviews.
and so they do like online but there basically doing a phone screw right so they're doing that first round interview.
but then you still have to go on-site afterwards.
and so it could it could potentially give you a good opportunity to break in to get on to get into that on-site interview. but then you're still.
gonna run into the same issues.
so I honestly don't know I don't think there is a great solution.
because just inherently you know you look at for example this is a problem obviously that people have been trying to fix everywhere for years.
like you look at like college admissions right.
and so you had this I think I saw an article recently that was or watched a video that was about Harvard admissions.
and the sort of racial makeup of the admissions like statistics and there were a.
bunch of Asian students who were actually suing Harvard for basically being even.
even though the Harvard student body is made up of a disproportionate number of Asian students.
they still accept them as a way lower percentage of the total applicants.
because there is this skew just naturally that the you know Asian students are trying to get there are a lot of Asian students trying to get into Harvard.
and a lot of really smart Asian students.
and so the question is with that it's like what do.
you do and so Harvard you know they're trying to balance things and balance people from different backgrounds but there is no good solution.
and if they were to do things the other way if they were to say okay we'll take Asian students proportionally.
then the african-american students would be really upset because they're getting shortchanged.
or though you know the white students would get really upset it's kind of a zero-sum game right.
where if one person gets it another person does it.
and so there's always gonna.
be this push and pull where you can try and implement things to make it more fair to one group.
but inherently by doing that you're making it less fair to another group.
and I don't I don't know I think this is something that people have been trying to figure out for you know hundreds of years at this point.
and I have no idea what the solution is.
yeah it is a very difficult problem in general and of course it's not typically it's AK problem is a.
hiring problem in general but that just tends to have already a very biased population.
so that or a skewed population towards certain categories.
so that might increase the problem makers and that's what people people think about a computer nerd or about a programmer.
and they might have a specific person in you.
but let's move on to a lighter topic.
so you have yourself done a bunch of interviews and before the show you told me that you might have some failures to share with people. and maybe.
also some lessons learned from failures in interviews.
so is there any cool story you could tell that it's funny now about interviews that you fail that.
yeah I definitely share failed my fair share of interviews.
and I think the the one that I can laugh about the best is probably the very first interview that I ever did was my freshman year of college.
so I'd basically taken half of intro to computer science and I had an interview with Microsoft.
so they were doing like interviews on.
campus and I went in and the guy was kind of intimidating I'd never done anything like this before.
before the interview I had picked up cracking the coding interview and I looked through it.
I was like half of this stuff is stuff that I have never heard of before.
and then I think I went in and he asked me to describe to him an array or something super simple.
and I was like what's an array like it was that it was the most basic level problem.
and I just had no clue.
so that was obviously I did not get the internship at that point.
and it was you know it was one of those things where obviously I was in this position where I did not have the background. but I think that.
you know a lot of times we do end up in this situation where we tend to be so hard on ourselves.
and I like to realize that you know we're all coming from somewhere and they're all learning experiences right.
so.
that was a great position where I was in this experience and I was like holy crap I had no idea what to do.
so now how do i improve for the future how do I move ahead for my future interviews.
rather than getting like bent out of shape and saying oh well I felt this one interview.
and so I'm never going to be successful.
yeah that's a good lesson in general I thing that if you fill an interview it might also just be the fit between.
you and that company and that point of course it doesn't necessarily mean that you are bad at programming.
I want to highlight something you just said as well because you said it might not be a good fit at that point.
and I think that's actually you know what arrays are now yeah.
but that's like one of the biggest lessons that I would take away from this in general.
because it's like I see a lot of people where they are hesitant to interview at all.
because they're. like this is my one shot.
and a lot of times it's something more subtle it's not something like they don't know what an array is.
I assume most people who are interviewing to.
but it's a matter of saying you know maybe I wasn't as prepared for the interviews.
I didn't do as well as I wanted to.
but that does not mean that you get blacklisted from the company.
so like I interviewed at Google my senior year of college and did not get in and then about.
nine months later I had a recruiter reach out to me again and be like hey do you want to interview again.
and then I interviewed again and went through that process and then I did not end up doing that.
and then nine months later someone reached out to me again.
and it's been like now I'm actually not looking for software engineering jobs because I'm really focused on running my company.
but I'm constantly getting reached out to from recruiters who are at companies where I had previously.
failed interviews and so it's so much better for you to actually go out and put yourself out there and go through the process.
and then realize maybe I did well maybe I didn't but you never know until you actually go through the process.
and I think so many people waste so much time just studying and studying and studying and studying.
because they don't feel 100% ready that they never actually go into the interview.
and maybe like you know six months ago you could have gone in.
and done the interview successfully but you weren't feeling confident about it so you just didn't do it.
ya know so every interview is also a learning opportunity.
so if you don't get the job then at least you get another insight in with type of questions or ask for exactly protest.
so it's also a matter of just embracing failure as learning motivation I guess.
yeah a thousand percent because you don't know what to expect until you've actually gone and done the process.
and that's also like you.
know recommend people do mock interviews leading up to your real interview.
or do interviews at companies that you're less excited about first.
and then you can go and do interviews at you know your dream company after you've had a chance to do some other interviews and get prepared.
and get to start to understand that process.
that's actually already the answer to the question I was going to ask you.
because I wanted to ask you how do people get better at interviews. and I think you're any.
mention two things practice mock interviews and also just interview at companies you're not super excited about.
what would your other tips be for people to practice this interview.
and if it maybe let's zoom into this mock interview a bit more like who does a mock interview with me.
if I want to apply my friends another company how does that mock interview process work.
and what other tips do you have.
yeah absolutely because this is really my bread and butter is helping people to prepare for these. interviews.
and so there are a couple things that you know all sort of I'll share with you.
a couple of the different things that you know we've really been thinking about recently.
so the first is I generally like to think about interview prep broadly as what I call the three pillars of interviewing.
and so the three pillars of interviewing basically breaks down into the CS fundamentals the strategy and building your self-confidence.
and sort of by extension your social skills and social and like ability to interact.
with people in the interview.
and so the reason why I sort of lay these out is I think that.
if you just focus on these three things that's gonna get you 80 to 90 percent of the way there.
because if you think about it for starters like knowing those data structures and algorithms is so important.
it's like we were talking about how there's a bias towards people who have a computer science degree right.
because you've studied those things before and I think about it like I.
love to use sports analogies because it just not because I actually like sports that much but because it's just a parallel so well.
so if you think about like playing you know basketball before you can learn before you can apply like some crazy strategy.
you got to learn how to dribble the ball you got to learn how to shoot.
you got to learn how to pass you got to learn these basic skills right.
and then those sort of make up the actual basketball game. so with.
coding interviews that's learning all of those basics data structures and algorithms that sort of underlie everything else.
and a great easy resource for that I really like cracking the coding interview.
if you go on if you own a copy of it that's great.
if you don't own a copy you can literally go on amazon.com and go to the table of contents.
like go to the thing where you can like look inside the book go to the table of contents.
and you can see exactly what topics.
you need to stuff so that's a great like quick easy resource there.
but but also if you value people's work just buy their books.
yes absolutely I do think you should buy the book no question.
but if you're not going to buy the book for whatever reason you can still benefit from at least the table of contents.
fair enough is there anything else that we could do like okay read the book practice interviews.
any other tips to really nail that interview maybe before we before you.
go apply at their company you're really excited about then you actually want to work.
well so I think the other two big things that are super important with this are being strategic number one.
so like being strategic when I work with a lot of people the general approach that people take to interview prep.
and for everyone listening out there just take a moment and think if this is you or not is that you go into the interview.
and you basically say I hope that I either.
see a problem that I've already seen before or that I'm gonna be able to look at the problem and immediately see a solution.
and that's or the standard way that people approach this.
but the problem with that is that that leaves a lot of room for error.
because if you go into the interview you basically are setting up this dichotomy where it's like either I see the solution to the problem.
or I don't see the solution to the problem.
and so what I really want to.
encourage people to think about is how can I be more strategic about how I'm approaching the problems.
how can I make sure that I have a sort of framework that I can use to tackle these problems regardless of whether I've seen them before.
so the basic framework that I recommend to people is you know start with finding that brute force solution to the problem.
don't worry about finding an optimal solution start by finding that brute force solution.
then kind of take a step wise process of. optimizing.
so like in cracking the coding interview she talks about the bud optimization strategy.
which is bottlenecks unused code and duplicated work.
and those are sort of things to look for in your code to start optimizing.
and then only at that point do you actually go and write the code in your interview.
and then finally you got to test the code as well.
so just even you know I can go into so much more detail about the individual steps of the framework. but at a high.
level just having that step by step process of this is how I'm going to approach the problem when I go into the interview makes such a huge difference.
and then the third thing was of course the social skills which you know and building that confidence.
which that's really where the things that we were talking about the mock interviews.
you know doing interviews at companies you're less excited about.
there are a couple great resources for mock interviews so one highly encourage you you know find a friend.
and do like partner up you know you can mock interview then they can mock interview you really easy solution.
there's also pram comm which give which facilitates free peer-to-peer mock interviews.
and I think if you go to byte by byte comm slash cramp you can also get we have a thing with them where you'll get unlimited credits.
and so you can do as many mock interviews as you want.
there are pros and cons to it because obviously it's a peer to peer so you're not necessarily.
going to get the best feedback because you're working with someone else who is also learning.
but it's a great opportunity for you to also put yourself in the shoes of the interviewer and get experience doing that.
and then interviewing dot IO as well is a great resource if you are slightly more senior.
so I know that they're primarily looking for people who are in a slightly more senior development position like four or five years or more of experience.
but if you're in that demographic that's a.
really good resource as well.
so those are a couple ways that you can actually get that practice.
we will definitely add those links to the show notes.
and let's now move on to the site of the interviewer that you also you just hinted as already imagine.
and if you do this period or your thing you will imagine that you are an interviewer.
so do you also have some best practices for people that do interviews.
many of our listeners might actually sometimes be involved or actually do.
themselves entirely the technical interviews from the interviewer perspective.
you how do you get better at that.
yeah absolutely so I'm going to start by saying let's get really meta about this.
and just like I said imagine it as an interviewee imagine putting yourself in the position of the interviewer.
as an interviewer you want to imagine yourself in the position of the interviewee right.
so you want to understand like what is the perception of the person coming in.
how do I make them comfortable how do I.
set up a position a situation that is going to be better for them.
so like right off the bat a couple things and like you know this is also partially from my experience.
I've had a lot of bad interviews where I've been the interviewee and the interviewer has done something that's really made me feel uncomfortable.
or made me have trouble in the interview.
so a couple things that I would say right off the bat are one make sure that you try and be warm and friend.
as warm and friendly with the person as you can.
a lot of interviewees are super nervous coming in they're not feeling comfortable.
talk to them you know have a little bit of small talk conversation.
make sure that they're feeling comfortable if they need water or coffee or a bathroom break or whatever.
because a lot of times when you're doing interviews it's like they're doing four or five interviews in a row.
and you're just coming in here for the hour or whatever but they've been like doing.
these back-to-back-to-back and so they're gonna be kind of fried potentially when they get to you.
so a couple things like that making that a little bit of small talk.
one thing that I would recommend that you know some people do and some people don't is ask the same question to all of your interviewees.
because when you ask the same question it allows you to not only evaluate people in a more objective way.
because everyone is doing the same work and so you can compare them better.
it also is going to show you it's going to give you a much better sense of like what are the sort of ins and outs of the problem.
what are the things that people tend to get tripped up on.
you kind of have this like Bank of hints that you're able to give people depending on where they get stuck. and so I think that. can be really helpful.
and when you're choosing the problem as well one thing that I really really like it makes your life.
so much easier as an interviewer is do a multi-part problem where the first part is really easy.
so if you do a multi-part problem where the first part is easy this accomplishes two things.
one is it helps your interviewer you interviewee feel a little bit more comfortable as they're going through.
because you know they can get that quick win early on.
and so it'll help them feel like loosen up a bit more and you know free them up to really show you what they can do.
and then second of all it makes it so that if you have someone come in who's clearly just not good at this and is not figuring it out.
I like having a problem where if they get stuff for 45 minutes on the easy part of the problem.
at the end we can walk through the solution together and they feel good about it.
because I don't want it to like I don't I've had cases where I've gotten to the end of the interview and they're like totally.
stuck and I'm like oh let's talk through this together.
and they're just I try and explain it and it's still just going completely over their head.
and that always just feels like crap so I really try to avoid that.
and then the other thing that when you do a multi-part problem is that once you get through that first part.
I like to give them I and this is again my personal preference.
I like to give them a problem set or a second part of the problem.
that's open-ended and does not have a oftentimes I like one that doesn't have like a singular optimal solution.
because what I think is most valuable is let's have a discussion it comes more to the pair of programming side of things.
it's like let's discuss the trade-offs here let's discuss like how we might you know weigh our different options.
and figure out what is the best solution here.
and if you pick something that's kind of open-ended and and doesn't necessarily have a single optimal solution that facilitates.
a lot more conversation and a lot more discussion which I think can get really interesting.
especially that's where you can start to see where a candidate where candidates can start to shine really.
because you can have it's like when you can start to have a deeper technical conversation with them.
and they've already valid it they already did the first part they already validated for you that they have the basic technical skills.
now let's dig deeper and like see how far we can push things. nice those. are such considerate tips.
it's an interviewer you are thinking about also a good experience for someone as being interviewed.
to help them maybe try such an interview again at a next company.
I think that's that's very very valuable. I do think that's really really important.
and I think that that's something that you know interviewing can often be you know it's something that.
kind of gets thrown in your lap.
as a distraction from what you're normally doing. but it also makes it a more fun experience for.
both of you if you just take a little bit of time to think about how can I make this an enjoyable experience for both of us.
nice so we just talked about failure from the interviewee.
Sam is there also a nice interviewers and failure story that you have to share.
where she's like from the second the interviewee came in you're like oh there's just they don't have an understanding of what this job was all about.
or just it was a mismatch and then and yeah it's.
sort of a board or pull someone true.
I think you sort of hinted that this already at one point you gave someone a complicated exercise.
and you explained the answer and then still it in together which community is not really a great experience.
do you have any other interviewers and failure stories.
yeah I mean that's sort of where I was thinking when you asked this question.
I think you know one of my favorite sorts of questions to ask is like a basic recursion question. so for.
example come up with all the come up with like a power center.
come up with all the combinations of a series of inputs.
and so if you understand recursion it's fairly straightforward it's a pretty easy thing to do.
and it's also you know just side note if you're going to be interviewing and you're gonna study recursion.
that is the one thing if you just know how to do that super super useful.
so side note but I I think it was I was working with a client.
and so I this was the first time that I had done a mock interview with them or anything.
and I asked them this question and they were like totally stumped.
because they obviously didn't really have much recursion experience in this case.
and I just felt terrible because I'm this is a new client that I'm working with.
and so now I'm putting them as at this position where they feel like a total idiot.
and I'm like this is completely my fault and so I shifted after that.
point to say again basically what I was saying is I will in that case I would just ask them two separate questions.
but ask them a easy question first and then only once they get through that then let's say okay you did great on this beginner question.
now let's get into the meat and if you struggle with this well at least we have an idea of you know your between your somewhere between point A.
and point B.
rather than we just have no idea because I.
just asked you a question that was really hard and made you totally demoralized about your whole process of preparing for your interviews.
so we briefly talks about this in the beginning of the interviews I think where you said oh sometimes also within interviews people do debugging or testing.
and I want to zoom in that's a little bit more as the final topic of this episode.
typically those algorithmic questions are very much aimed at creating an algorithm.
so give me the algorithm or give me the code.
for doing such and such.
I can imagine it it's also interesting to know or important.
you know if a candidate can debugger in them for example is this something you know.
where people say here is code with a bug in it find the code.
or here is code that doesn't have tests write some sensible tests.
and using tests try to find the bug.
yeah so my old company that I used to work for did exactly the first thing that you said is they would give you.
an actual program and it had I think four or five specific bugs in it.
and the idea was basically they wanted you to use whatever use all the tools available to you to identify what those bugs were and fix it. so that it would run properly.
and so it's really you know with that sort of problem it was really about how do you be systematic about this.
because I think a lot of times will jump in and you know even I know I do this for.
my own code a lot of the time when I'm testing you know I wrote something and I'm like why isn't it working.
I just kind of read through the code and stare at it a little bit.
and think about it and wonder you know why the programming gods are not favouring me today.
and it doesn't actually help me figure out what's wrong.
and so I tend to go through like the you know eight stages of green for whatever it is.
and then ultimately I finally get.
to the acceptance of I need to write some tests of actually test this thing.
but this that's really what I think in the tuba in the debugging interview.
specifically in that sort of interview you really want to be able to jump straight to that.
and say okay I'm gonna be strategic about this.
I'm gonna you know for instance let's figure out where I can set you know five different breakpoints in this code.
we're gonna be the breakpoints what am I gonna expect the data to be.
and so you can start you know very quickly start to narrow stuff down and figure out okay well what function is in correct or right.
basic unit tests right.
there are a lot of ways that you can approach it but it's really about being strategic.
and about you know using the tools available to you.
so like in that case I believe we were using Eclipse.
and so it's one of those cases where it is a matter of you kind of need to understand the IDE at.
least in a basic level.
because in that case I was programming in Java so we were using Eclipse for that.
but I mean if I had questions about specifics of like you know how do I create a breakpoint that's not really the question at stake.
it's like you know I would expect as the interviewer to give people that sort of feedback especially if they haven't used the tool before.
yeah so it's basically like that would be one type of interview.
I think if you're more if.
you're looking at more of a QA or testing role.
I could I've not actually seen this but I would not be surprised if someone asks you to write a series of you know unit tests or integration tests. or something for a piece of code.
because I think that would be a really good interview if that is more of the job that. you're looking.
yeah so then we're back to the alignment between what you do and what your job will be. if you're gonna be a tester.
and I'm writing tests actually might make lots of sense maybe more and I'm writing cold.
yeah and that's also something I think that.
with testing it's a little bit more objective.
and there's a like see here's the thing is that with testing if I say okay I want you to write tests that will give me 90% coverage.
then that's a very easily measurable thing right.
I can literally use a tool to tap to my test coverage.
or I can say there are a series of bugs.
in here and so how many of those bugs are these tests catch it.
and then you know there's some subjective stuff like are they clean are they easy to read are they you know maintainable stuff like that.
but at a very simple level I think writing tests is something that's a lot more objective.
and so that makes it the type that would make it potentially a really good way to test someone in that sort of situation.
great so those were all the questions that I had.
for you today the final question we always ask people on the show is where can we find out more about you and about the work you do.
yeah absolutely so you know my websites bite by bite comm it's B YT e - bi b YT e.com.
and we do have a couple resources that people might find interesting.
if you go to bite by bite calm slash 50 questions you can download.
we have a guide of 50 of the most common coding interview questions that you can.
download and we have like video walkthroughs of all of those.
and as you mentioned at the beginning we also have a ebook on dynamic programming that's free as well.
so people want to go - that's just dynamic programming book comm.
so those would be great resources.
you can also find me on youtube actually we do a lot of YouTube videos.
so you can just search for bite by bite on YouTube and that'll come up.
but that would be you know I'd love to connect with anyone. who listens to this and would like to learn more.
because definitely you know we're here to help if you're preparing for your coding interviews in any way.
yeah we'll definitely make sure that the YouTube and your own website and ebook and 50 questions that those are all in the show notes.
so if people are interested they can easily find it to our website.
perfect so thanks so much for being on the show today Sam.
yeah thank you so much for having me this is super fun.
developers take your marks it's time.
to upgrade your data platform to inner systems iris. it's time.
to deliver complex mission-critical applications in the fastest route possible. it's time.
to use any data from any source. it's time.
to embed analytics and create interactive user interfaces.
so what are you waiting for choose your language choose your tools choose your environment.
collaborate build faster and deploy more efficiently.
done and done tomorrow's next breakthroughs are waiting for you today.
inner system's iris a platform the fastest way to build applications.
ready set code start coding for free visit inner systems.com slash tried to try iris.
thanks for listening the SC radio an educational program brought to you by Triple E software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website @ SC - radio net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our slack channel at SC radio.com.
you can also email us at team @ SC - radio net this and all.
other episodes of SU radio is licensed under Creative Commons license 2.5.
thanks for listening.